So we'll now speak to board effectiveness.
I've described the duties and responsibilities of the
board but those are the basics, the very
basics.
A board has to be effective for it
to add value to the business.
So let's call board effectiveness, we'll take a
short case study of how Facebook acquired Instagram.
So Mark Zuckerberg owned at the point this
case study came up 28% of Facebook
stock and controlled 57% of its voting
rights.
Facebook's public offering was only a few weeks
away.
On the other hand, Kevin owned about 45
% of Instagram.
The company at the time was 18 months
old, employed 13 people, had 35 million users,
nil revenue.
On Thursday the 5th of April 2012, Zuckerberg
picked up his phone and asked Kevin for
a meeting.
Over the next three days, which happened to
be over the weekend, the two CEOs negotiated
in the privacy of Zuckerberg's home.
On Sunday morning, April the 8th, Zuckerberg emailed
his board that he wanted to buy Instagram.
On Monday, the deal was announced.
So a few things would have happened here,
you know, like I said, or like the
case facts say, the public offering of Facebook
was just a few weeks away.
If the deal to buy Instagram had gone
wrong, it would have significantly affected the public
offering.
Why did Zuckerberg not involve his board in
this negotiation?
A few reasons would come to mind.
One of which is the fact that Zuckerberg
seemingly had control of the board.
He was the one that appointed almost all,
in fact, all of the board members because
essentially he owned the company.
And so he appointed a few of his
cronies as members of the board.
So they didn't really have a say in
the governing of the organisation.
Second thing, and this is very much true
of tech companies, he felt that the board
might not have an understanding of the gravity
of the opportunity.
And he felt that he was slowed down
or bogged down by the bureaucracy of holding
a board meeting and taking the trouble to
explain to the board.
Some people have also said perhaps the board
had given him a significant or delegated to
him a significant portion of their authority.
But regardless, acquisition, mergers and acquisitions, and a
transaction of this nature should not or could
not have been delegated to the CEO.
Critically, the board should have considered the pros
and cons of such a major acquisition and
the impact of it on particularly the impending
public offer of Facebook.
Fortunately for Zuckerberg and the board and the
company as a whole, the deal has succeeded
as we can see how profitable the addition
of Instagram to the business has been.
But this underscores the effectiveness of the board.
How effective would one say that board was?
In my opinion, very ineffective because again, it
could have caused significant losses to the business.
And so we go on to the definition
of an effective board as described by the
Nigerian Code of Corporate Governance, which I will
read.
It says a successful company is headed by
an effective board which is responsible for providing
entrepreneurial and strategic leadership, as well as promoting
ethical, cultural and responsible corporate citizenship.
As a link between stakeholders and the company,
the board is to exercise oversight and control
to ensure that management acts in the best
interest of shareholders and other stakeholders while sustaining
the prosperity of the company.
This is taken from principle one of the
Nigerian Code of Corporate Governance.
So essentially, beyond meeting the basics like we
have described in the course of this session,
the board also has to be effective.
The board has to provide entrepreneurial and strategic
leadership.
That's why many boards go to the trouble
of identifying directors who can add value beyond
just attending meetings and providing the regular oversight
and they have to provide leadership to the
business.
So broken down, the role of the board
can be described as that of providing accountability.
The board puts itself in a position where
management is accountable to it.
And one of the ways that the board
can be accountable to the board is what
we had described earlier.
The board sets key performance indicators and measures
the performance of management against these key performance
indicators.
So management knows that it is accountable to
a body and not just accountable to itself.
The board on the other hand is accountable
to shareholders who have appointed ostensibly the directors.
The board also provides leadership.
Now this leadership is not academic.
The leadership is actually leadership that is responsible
for strategy and direction.
The board sets the tone in terms of
where the business is headed and allows management
to provide strategic initiatives to achieve the said
strategy.
The board is the one that sets the
ethical tone, what we describe as the tone
at the top.
And that tone is defined by the kind
of people that we hire, how we evaluate
performance and how we reward and punish bad
behaviour.
The board is also expected to measure and
monitor performance.
We have spoken about that earlier.
The board is responsible for risk management, ensuring
that the financial statements present a true and
fair view and also managing succession planning and
business continuity.
We saw during COVID that a number of
organisations did not survive COVID because they didn't
have robust business continuity plans that would ensure
that whatever the crisis, whatever the nature of
the crisis, the organisation is able to go
beyond.
That also affects succession planning.
The board should not leave the issue of
succession planning at critical levels in the organisation
to management.